A Guide to the Monticello Music Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Part 2: Music from the library of Thomas Jefferson
  - Songs with texted verses and keyboard instrument with figured bass and/or the German flute and/or guitar accompaniment.
    The Bee set to music by Mr. Collett, The Adieux set by Mr. Oswald, Robin Hood sung by Mr. Beard, The Maying sung by Mrs. Pope, Bacchus sung by Mr. Taylor, The Fairest of the Fair sung at Ranelagh, By My Sighs, The Rose, A New Song Come Damon, come, oh haste away ..., A Drinking Song sung at Sadler's Wells, The Banquet - A Drinking Song, Jolly Bacchus, The Farmer's Description of London- A Medley, Cupid God of Soft Persuasion sung by Miss Hallam in Love in a Village, Damon - A New Song the word by a Lady, set by Mr. Leonard Abingdon, Volamente, a Rondeau by Giardini, The Jolley Brisk Tarr, A Two-Part Song set by Mr. H. Purcell Fill, fill, fill all the Glasses ..., The Mighty Bowl, A Song for Three Voices Made on the Peace ..., A Song with a Trumpet set by Mr. Henry Purcell Genius of England ..., A New Song Give us Glasses my Wench ..., Lovely Nancy With Variations, A Song Set to Musick by Mr. Fisher How Wellcome My Shepard ..., Sung by Mr. Prentice at Sadler's Wells I'm a Hearty Good Fellow ..., Sung by Mr. Jagger at Vauxhall In fancy our hopes and fears ..., The Pilgrim, The Serenade sung by Mr. Mattocks in the Merchant of Venice, My Bliss too long my Bride Denies ..., Jockey, A Favorite new Scotch Ballad sung by Mr. Baddeley at Vauxhall (2 copies), In Praise of Woman sung by Mr. Prentise at Sadlers Wells, The Second Ode of Anacreon, Woman sung by Mr. Lowe at Vauxhall, set by Mr. J. Soaper, A Bacchanalian Song, Content - a pastoral from Mr. Cunningham's Collection, set by Mr. Goodwin, Time Made Prisoner A Favorite Song, Throw the Wood Lassie or Sawny's Return To Music by Mr. Arne, The Honest Fellow set by Dr. Arne, The Ass- A New Song in the Chaplet, A New Song Push About the Brisk Glass ..., Platos's Advice, The Cottager sung by Mr. Cooke at Sadlers Wells, Delia set by Dr. Arne, A Song in Love in a Village Sung by Mr. Mattocks set by Dr. Arne Still in Hopes to Get the Better of My Stubborn Flame I Try ... - Young Meadows' Song in Love in a Village, Bird sung by Mr. Raworth at Marybone Gardens, set by Mr. Snow, May Eve, or Kate of Aberdeen sung by Mr. Hudson at Ranelagh and Miss Polly Young at Vauxhall, The Full Flowing Bowl sung by Mr. Lowe at Marybone Gardens, The Charms of a Bumper sung at the Publick Gardens On Friendship set by Mr. J Gerard, A Song This World is a Stage ..., Russell's Triumph, Thy Father Away sung by Mr. Beard in Artaxerxes, Make Hay Whilst the Sun Shines set by Mr. Hudson, The Spinning Wheel sung by Miss Thomas at Ranelagh, set by Mr. W. Goodwin, To Keep My Gentle Jessy A favorite song in the Merchant of Venice, set by Dr. Arne, A Drinking Song To Some Petty Sinner Go Wheedle and Whine ..., Well, Well, Say No More ... sung by Mr. Dunstall [from Love in a Village], There Was a Jolly Miller ... sung by Mr. Beard [from Love in a Village], The Right Thinker sung by Mr. Cooke at Sadlers Well, When All the Attic Fire was Fled ..., Rule Britannia set to music by Dr. Arne, The Confession set by Mr. Walter Claget, Anacreon on Himself, The Evening Adventure, Nottingham Ale, The Bacchanalian While I quaff the rosy wine ..., Love and Wine in Alliance set to music by Mr. Arne, A Drinking Song Whilst I'm Carrouzing ..., The Bacchanalians Sung by Mr. Howard at the theatre Royal in Covent Garden Wine, Wine is Alone ye Brisk Fountain of Mirth ..., Woman for Man Adressed to the Batchelors, The New Year's Gift, Delia by Mr. Squibb at Marybone Gardens, set to music by Mr. W Jackson, English Ale sung by Mr. Prentis at Sadlers Well, The Union of Love and Wine sung by Mr. Lowe at Vauxhall, Addressed to the Ladies at Ranelagh by Mr. Whitehead, Sparkling Champaign sung by Mr. Lowe at Marybone Garden, composed by Mr. Collet, Ye Fair Married Dames ... from The Way to Keep Him by Dr. Arne, sung by Mrs. Cibber, A Drinking Song Ye Famed Witty Nine ... sung by Mr. Lowe in Praise of the Half-Moon Society, the music by Mr. Bates, Sung by Mr. Prentice at Sadlers Well Ye Lads and Ye Lasses Who Bloom in Your Prime ..., A Favorite Song composed by Mr. James Ye Mortals that Love Drinking ..., The Triumph of Bacchus wrote by Mr. Gibson, set by Mr. Goodwin, A Song in Lethe sung by Mercury, Ye Mortals Whom Fancies and Troubles Perplex ..., Bacchus' Invitation, Bagnigge Wells, Miss Dawson's Hornpipe with variations, Jack Latin with Variations composed by Miss Elizabeth Mitford.
- Part 3: Music manuscript book, Microfilm
  Supposedly belonged to Martha Jefferson Randolph. Several unidentifiable selections and fragments of selections, along with the following listing.
  Sonata du Mecirc;me, Simphonie del Signor Wonesch, Sonata Del Signor Ernest Eichner, Rondo par Mr. Balbastre, [Italian song] sung by Sigr. Pacchierotti, Ma Chère Amie, by Sigr. Hook, The Mansion of Peace, [Italian song] by del Signor Mortellari Airs Variés, par Mr. Charpentier, Organiste, Aria Matinore Musette, Aria Triste Raison, La Petitte Poste de Paris, Menuet de Fischer, Air des Amours D'Eté, Les Folies D'Espagnes Variées, Ouverture La Buona Figliuola, La Triomphante, -- sonata, Ouverture de Chimene, Ballet de Chimene, Choeur des Voyageurs, -- de la Caravanne, Rondeau par J. B. Krumpholtz, Ouverture D'Iphigenie en Aulide, Symphonie del Signor Krumpholtz, March Querrier, par Mr. Balbastre, La Canonade, du Mecirc;me, Symphonie du Mecirc;me, La De Villiers du Même, Sonata del Signor Scarlati, Les Sauvages, by Mr. Rameau, In This Still Retirement and Let Not Age Thy Bloom Ensnare, by Mr. Haydn, Pleyel's Celebrated Quartette from his 5th suite called Le Tout Ensemble, Pleyel's German Hymn with Variations - Children of the Heavenly King, Adeste Fideles, Duetto del Signor Vicenzo Martini.
- Part 4: Music manuscript notebook, Microfilm
  This notebook allegedly belonged to Martha Wayles Skelton Jefferson. Contains handwritten music and lyrics to several songs, transcriptions of various short keyboard pieces and solo melodies, music theory exercises, notes on performance practice, and figured bass. Appears to be a pedagogical workbook.
  Minuet by Mr. Clarke, Camilla, Almaine, by Mr. Clarke, Celia has a thousand charms, Arietta Bononcini - for Camilla, Aurelia Singing, by Mr. Clarke, The Silver Swans, by Mr. Jeremiah Clarke, Love and Folly, Fate has decried us, Boast No More, Fond Love, Corant, Epithalamium Once Cloris Did Fly Me..., A Ground, Symphony, Grave, Hither, hither, gentle shepherd ..., If You In Love Such Tickling Joys, My Song Shall Be Always of the Loving Kindness of the Lord, Ground by Corelli [Sonata, op. 5, no. 12, Follia con variaziones], The Ponjury Son, in Indian Queen, A Song, by Mr. Purcell, A Song in The Tempest, by Mr. Purcell, An Italian Song, The Chorus in The Fairy Queen, Chorus in The Prophetess.
- Part 5: Monticello Music Collection
  Collection of sheet music, hand-stitched together with string. Some of the pieces are individual editions of songs in sheet music form; a few are selections cut from other volumes. Inscribed: "Elizabeth Virginia Lightfoot" and "Elizabeth Virginia Nicholas" in several places. Most of these pieces of music date from the 1790s. There is no way of telling how or when they came into the possession of the Jefferson family. The following list contains as much information on each piece of music in this folder as is available. Acc. No. 71-6331.
  - The Caledonian Laddy. (Folder Folder A)
    Printed by Benjamin Carr and sold at his musical repositories in Philadelphia and New York, and by I. Carr in Baltimore. This edition represents pp. 2-3 in The favorite songs by Mr. Hook, published in Philadelphia, [ca. 1794-95]. Song with pianoforte accompaniment, with text in three verses, and optional guitar part. Voice/pianoforte in D-major. Guitar in C-major.
    Pauvre Jaque. Also printed for Carr, [ca. 1796]. Song with pianoforte accompaniment. French and English words. Below the title is printed, NB The small notes with the tails downwards must be sung to the French words. This copy is rather washed out, and somebody has gone over parts of it with ink, to make the printing clearer. Sonneck (p. 327) gives Madame B. de Travanet as the composer.
    Ma Belle Coquette: A Favorite Song Composed by Mr. Hook. Song with pianoforte accompaniment, with text in four verses. Printed for G. Willig, 165 Market St., Philadelphia, [ca. 1795-97] where may be had a great Variety of the newest Vocal and Instrumental Music. Autographed by Elizabeth Virginia Nicholas bottom of page 2.
    Here's the Pretty Girl I Love: Composed by Mr. Hooke. Song with pianoforte accompaniment, with text in three verses. Printed for J. Hewitt's musical repository, 131 William St., New York; Published, Jan., 1798. Sold also by B Carr Philadelphia & J Carr Baltimore. Price: 25 Cts.
    Negro Philosophy: Written, composed, and sung by Mr. Dibdin in his new entertainment, called the General Election. Song with Pianoforte accompaniment, text in four verses. Printed and sold at J. Hewitt's Musical Repository 121 William St., New York. Price: 25 Cts. Sold also by B. Carr Philadelphia and J. Carr Baltimore. About a third of the second page has been cut off.
    The Confession: A favorite canzonet with an accompaniment for harp or pianoforte, the music by an amateur. Song with text in four verses. French words for first verse penciled in. About a third of the third page has been cut off. Printed by Longman and Broderip, 26 Cheapside and 13 Haymarket, London, Ent. At Stationers Hall. Price: $1.00.
    The Sailor's Journal by Dibdin. Song with Pianoforte accompaniment, with text in six verses. [Also titled Nancy or Nancy, or the Sailor's Journal.] Printed at B. Carrs Musical Repositories New York & Philadelphia & J. Carrs Baltimore, 1797. Price: 25 Cents. About a third of the second page has been cut off.
    Meg of Wapping. Written & Composed by Mr. Dibdin & sung by him in his New Entertainment called General Election. Song with pianoforte accompaniment, with text in five verses. Printed & sold at J. Jewitt's Musical Repository No. 131 Williams Street, New York. Sold also by B. Carr Philadelphia & J. Carr Baltimore, published Dec. 1797-Jan. 1798. About half of the second page has been cut off. Price: 25 Cts.
    The Patent Coffin: Written and Composed by Mr. Dibdin. Song with pianoforte accompaniment. Printed & sold at J. Jewitt's Musical Repository No. 131 Williams Street, New York. Sold also by B. Carr Philadelphia & J. Carr Baltimore, 1797. Price: 25 Cts. Page 1 only.
    Sweet Nan of Hampton Green. Published by G. Willig, Philadelphia, Where may be had a great variety of the Newest Vocal and Instrumental Music. Song with pianoforte accompaniment, with text in three verses. Optional guitar part on second page. Sonneck gives Hook as the composer and 1792-93 as the publication date.[2] This edition is a separate issue.
    A celebrated duett in Artaxerxes: Fair Aurora Composed by Dr. Arne. Vocal duet with unspecified figured bass accompaniment. Published by Mr. Trisobio [Filippo Trisobio, 66 North Front St., Philadelphia, 1796-98]. About a quarter of the second page has been torn off.
    Did Not Tyrant Custom Guide Me. Dal Sengo song with pianoforte accompaniment. Written by Giordani, published by Trisobio (see above). This is a rather peculiar-looking edition, having the voice part written on the second of the three staves.
  - Pages 53-56 from No. 7 of The Gentleman's Amusement. ca. May, 1796.
    According to the Music Division, DLC, this copy of pp. 53-54 is the only extant copy of this page. See Oscar G. Sonneck, A Bibliography of Early Secular American Music. Revised and enlarged by William Treat Upton. The Library of Congress, Music Division, 1945. See also correspondence: Mrs. Helen Cripe to Music Division, DLC, from Curator's Office, Monticello, 10 Nov 1971, and Music Division, DLC, to Mr. Bear and Mrs. Cripe, 22 Nov 1971.
    - Unidentified, top of page 53.
      Song with unidentified treble accompaniment. Poetic text below. Perhaps last three lines of How Sweet When the Silver Moon, from The Purse or The Benevolent Tar by William Reeve.
      Written for & Sung by Mrs. Melmoth in The Children in the Wood [An opera by Samuel Arnold]. The Delights of Wedded Love, (First line: 'Mark, my Alford all the joys'). Vocal part, with text in three verses. Performed 2 Jan 1795, New York. Printed on the bottom half of p. 53.
      Sung by Mrs. Old Vixon in the Musical Farce called My Grandmother. Sold at Carr's Repository's Philadelphia. N. York & Baltimore. [Say How Can Words a Passion Feign.] Song with pianoforte accompaniment. From Stephen Storace's musical farce, My Grandmother, performed at the New Theater, Philadelphia, 27 April 1795. Price: 12 Cents.
      Favorite Country Dance Compos'd by Dibdin. Unaccompanied treble melody. Choreography indicated below staff.
      Within a Mile of Edinburgh: Introduced and Sung by Miss Broadhurst in the Musical Farce called My Grandmother. Song with pianoforte and flute accompaniment, with text in two verses. Price: 12 Cents.
      Ever Remember Me: From The Opera of The Pirates. [by Storace]. Single treble line with unspecified instrumental introduction followed by vocal melody, with text in three verses.
      Sung by Mrs. Bland in the Opera of The Prisoner [by Thomas Atwood]. The Drummer (1st line: 'How charming a camp is...'). Single treble line with unspecified instrumental introduction followed by vocal melody, incomplete.
  - The Happy Dreamer: A Ballad.
    No author or composer indicated. Song with pianoforte accompaniment. Printed and sold by G. Willig Market Street No. 185. Philadelphia, [ca. 1798-1804]. Top of second page torn. Partial melody written in ink on back of second page.
    Water Parted From the Sea. In Artaxerxes by Dr. Arne, and adorned with Italian graces by Mr. Trisobio. Song with pianoforte accompaniment. [Filippo Trisobio, 66 N. Front St., Philadelphia, 1796-98].
    In My Pleasant Native Plains: The Favourite Roundelay Sung by Miss Sully at the Pantheon Philadelphia. Song with pianoforte accompaniment with text in three verses. Printed and sold by G. Willig, 185 Market St., Philadelphia, [ca. 1798-18O4]. [From The Carnival of Venice, by Thomas Linley, Sr. Performed in Philadelphia, 1796-97, and in New York, 1798.]
    No More His Fears Alarming: An Admired New Song. Composed by Stephen Storace & sung by Sr. Storace in the Opera of The Pirates. Song with pianoforte accompaniment. From Stephen Storace's opera, The Pirates. Published by G. Willig, 165 Market St., Philadelphia, [ca. 1795-97].
    Two Bunches a Penny Primroses. Song with pianoforte, flute, and horn accompaniment with text in three verses. Optional guitar accompaniment. No publisher indicated, [ca. 1800].
    The Rose. Song with pianoforte accompaniment with text in two verses. This copy has no imprint. [The song was from Selima and Azor by Thomas Linley, Sr. It first appeared in a collection published in Philadelphia in 1789 by Alexander Reinagle, then as a separate piece of sheet music published by Willig, at the 185 Market St. address, ca. 1798-1804.]
  - Pages 17-30 of a collection of songs. (Folder Folder B)
    All of the pieces in this selection are written in one- or two-staff treble clef arrangements. Arrangements such as this were usually used for violin or flute. None of the songs have lyrics, any evidence of composers, or dates of composition and publication. They probably date from the early 19th century. The following tunes are in this collection: Oft in the Stilly Night, Buy a Broom, Wha'll Be King But Charlie, Willis Grand March, Quick Step, I've Been Roaming, The Rustic Reel, When Thy Bosom Heaves the Sigh, Love was Once a Little Boy, A Russian Quick Step, Blink Over the Burn, My Sweet Laddie, The Oracle Waltz, Let us Haste to Kelvin Grove, Boston Brigade March, LaFayettes Quick Step, Caspar, from Der Fryschutz, Laughing Chorus, in Der Freyschutz, Bertha, Henry, Caroline, Giovinetto Cavalier, The Plain Gold Ring, The Huntsman's Chorus, in Der Freischutz.
  - Collection of miscellaneous pieces of sheet music for voice and pianoforte hand-stitched with string., Collection condition: poor. Fragile, torn pages. (Folder Folder C)
    Time: A Favorite Sonnet, composed by Pleyel. Published by Edmund Lee, No. 2 Dame St., near the Royal Exchange, Dublin. Song with pianoforte accompaniment with text in three verses. [Also known as Sonnet to Time, and it appeared in published American collections, ca. 1799-1803.]
    How Sweet the Love that Meets Return: An Admir'd Song, sung by Mrs. Kennedy and composed by Mr. Hook. Song with pianoforte accompaniment with text in five verses. [Sonneck lists no known place or date of publication, but places it sometime in the 1790s.] About a third of the page has been cut off at bottom.
    Ca Ira: The Celebrated Air with French and English words. Published by Edmund Lee, No. 2 Dame St., near the Royal Exchange, Dublin. Song with pianoforte accompaniment. [Several American editions of this were available, 1793-96.] About a third of the page has been cut off at bottom.
    Come Blushing Rose: A Favorite Ballad, composed by Mr. Pleyel. Published by Edmund Lee, No. 2 Dame St., near the Royal Exchange, Dublin. Song with pianoforte accompaniment with text in two verses. [Published in America in 1795.] About a third of the page has been cut off at bottom.
    From Branch to Branch, sung by Signora Sestini in Gretna Green and Inroduc'd by her in Lionel and Clarissa [music by Dibdin, libretto by Bickerstaff]. Published by Anne Lee No. 2 Dame St., near the Royal Exchange, Dublin. Song with pianoforte accompaniment. [The opera was performed in Philadelphia in 1792, and in various places through the 1790s.]
    Dibdin's New Song of Poor Jack. Composed by Charles Dibdin. Song with pianoforte accompaniment with text in three verses. [No publisher identification on this sheet, but several editions of the song were published in America, 1794-98.]
    Ariette de Blaise et Babet avec accompagnement de harpe par Mr. D.G.D.V. [From Blaise et Babet, by N. Dezède. No publisher identification on this sheet, but several American editions of the Overture from Blaise et Babet were published in America, 1789-1800.] Song with pianoforte accompaniment and words in French. Bottom of pages 1 and 2 torn. Page 1 glued to another sheet of paper.
    My Heavy Heart: A favorite Scotch song sung by Miss Bertles, VauxHall. [Page no. 21 appears in upper right-hand corner. This indicates that it could be from A Collection of Favorite Songs, Divided into Two Books. Arranged by Alexander Reinagle. Published, Philadelphia, ca. 1789.] Song with pianoforte accompaniment and text in three verses. Autographed by Eliza M. Barclay on top of page.
    Canzonet: Adapted to one voice, composed by W. Jackson. [1st line: Time has not thinned my flowing hair. No. 22 in upper left-hand corner identifies it as the back of the preceding page from Reinagle's book. Half cadence on E suggests a missing second page.] Song with pianoforte accompaniment.
    Donald: A favorite Scots Song. [No publisher identification on this sheet. No. 25 in upper right-hand corner.] Song with pianoforte accompaniment with text in two verses.
    Moggy's Complaint of Jockey. No. 26 in upper left-hand corner on the back of the previous page. No other identification.
  - Nine pieces of music, pages 29, 39-48, from a book of B. F. Peale's arrangement for Spanish Guitar, published by G. E. Blake of Philadelphia, July 29, 1826. (Folder Folder D)
    Jefferson's granddaughters, Cornelia Randolph, Virginia Randolph Trist, and Septimia Randolph Meikleham, all played the guitar. Jefferson bought Virginia an expensive Spanish guitar in 1816, and there are many passages in the family correspondence that mention the fact that she played it, probably rather well. The date of this guitar music indicates that it was very likely used by Virginia, and perhaps later by Cornelia and Septimia. Loudon's Bonnie Woods and Braes, I'll Watch for Thee, Home [Home, Sweet Home], The Harper's Song, Slowly Wears the Day Love, Waters of Elle, The Castilian Maid, Come Chase that Starting Tear Away, Tis Love in the Heart.
  - One-page handwritten manuscript fragment, Row Gently Here -- A Popular Venetian Air, from [?] Melodies Arranged by [?]: R. Bishop... (Folder Folder E)
    Song with pianoforte accompaniment; verse fragments notated vertically on right margin. Reverse side contains reprise of anacrusis to measure seven through measure fourteen.
  - One-page sheet, "Flutt'ring Spread Thy Purple Pinions: A Much Admir'd New song Composed by Sam.L Jackson. [ca. 1778-1803]. (Folder Folder F)
    Song with pianoforte accompaniment with text in three verses and parts for guitar and German flute parts. Published by John Lee, No. 70 Dame St., at the corner of Eustace St., Dublin.
  - Two pieces of sheet music hand-stitched together with string. [ca. 1803-14]. (Folder Folder G)
    G. E. Blake came to the United States in 1793. The Timid Tear: The Words by Moore Esq, Music by Barry Esq. Song with pianoforte accompaniment and text in two verses. Published by G. E. Blake, No. 1 South 3rd. St., Philadelphia. Price: 25 cents. In Praise of the Fair: Adapted to the Popular French air, La Pipe de Tobac with a Flute Accompainment. Song with pianoforte accompaniment, text in three verses, and part for flute. Interestingly the voice part is indicated on the middle staff. Also published by Blake. Price: 25 cents.
  - Miscellaneous pieces of manuscript lyrics and music (Folder Folder H)
    Some in variations, written in various hands, one of them Martha Jefferson Randolph's. Copenhagen Waltz with Variations and Set by Webbe. Cottage Rondo composed by Holst. The Tyrolese Song of Liberty by Thomas Moore, Esq. Robin Adair, Composed by W. Reeve. Musette de Nina""The Coronach Music by Dr. Clarke of Cambridge [Words by Scott.] The Queen of Prussia's Waltz: Variations by L'abbé Gelinek.
    The following items are written on two sides of sheet on manuscript paper. Untitled. First line: Merrily every bosom boundeth. Merrily oh! Merrily oh... Mozart's Favorite Waltz, begins in the middle of the reverse side. [Possibly composed by Thomas Moore.] One page of manuscript lyrics: The Ill Wife [verses 2-6], Home, Sweet Home [2 verses, in hand of Martha Jefferson Randolph, inscribed "Tufton, April 2nd, 1827"], There's Nae Luck About the House [verses 2-5].
  - Fragment of a book of Scotch songs with pianoforte accompaniment. 1 May 1793 (Folder Folder I)